<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A resolution of three important questions (premis'd as a foundation to an intended exposition of the fourth and fifth chapters of the apocalypse) in answer to the late reverend and learned Dr. H. M. Wherein is shewed, I. That the fourth and fifth chapters of the Revelation, are properly a prophecy of things to come to pass after St. John's receiving of the vision of them.  II. That by opening of the book, Rev. v. is meant, of prefigured the explaining of it. III. That by the throne in both the said chapters, is meant a throne of God on Earth, and not in the highest heaven. By W. G. V. T.</title>
            <author>Garrett, Walter.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42414</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G271A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200685</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825091</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825091</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29464</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42414)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29464)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2029:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A resolution of three important questions (premis'd as a foundation to an intended exposition of the fourth and fifth chapters of the apocalypse) in answer to the late reverend and learned Dr. H. M. Wherein is shewed, I. That the fourth and fifth chapters of the Revelation, are properly a prophecy of things to come to pass after St. John's receiving of the vision of them.  II. That by opening of the book, Rev. v. is meant, of prefigured the explaining of it. III. That by the throne in both the said chapters, is meant a throne of God on Earth, and not in the highest heaven. By W. G. V. T.</title>
                  <author>Garrett, Walter.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>W. G. V. T. = Walter Garrett.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: More, Henry.  Apocalypsis apocalypseos.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the Durham University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>More, Henry, 1614-1687. --  Apocalypsis apocalypseos --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation IV-V --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29464:1"/>
            <p>A RESOLUTION Of three Important Queſtions (pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd as a Foundation to an intended Expoſition of the fourth and fifth Chapters of the <hi>Apocalypſe</hi>) in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the late Reverend and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Dr. <hi>H. M.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein is ſhewed,
<list>
                  <item>I. <hi>That the Fourth and Fifth Chapters of the</hi> Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, <hi>are properly a Prophecy of things to come to paſs after St.</hi> John<hi>'s receiving of the Viſion of them.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. <hi>That by</hi> Opening <hi>of the Book,</hi> Rev. v. <hi>is meant, or prefigured the</hi> Explaining <hi>of it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>III. <hi>That by the</hi> Throne <hi>in both the ſaid Chapters, is meant a Throne of God on</hi> Earth, <hi>and not in the higheſt</hi> Heaven.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>W. G. V. T.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:29464:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29464:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>AS to this little Treatiſe (the <hi>ſmallneſs</hi> whereof would eaſily be excus'd, if it were not alſo of it ſelf <hi>imperfect,</hi> as deſign'd in order only to ſome other thing) I deſire the Reader to take this following account. It is now more than four Years ago, ſince I wrote an <hi>Expoſition</hi> on the fourth and fifth Chapters of the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> and communicated it to ſome certain Friends, whom I thought beſt able to make a right Judgment of it; who, for the most part, modeſtly excuſing their unacquaintedneſs with theſe Studies, advis'd me to impart it to the famous Dr. <hi>H. M.</hi> To him therefore I diſpatch'd it; who, quite contrary to what I imagin'd, finding very little to ſay againſt the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars</hi> of my Expoſition, ſet himſelf wholly to overthrow the very <hi>Foundation</hi> on which I built; and which I thought ſo plain, that no body could have oppos'd it. In ſhort, the main, and (in effect) the only things that he objected, were the contrary Propoſitions to what I here aſſert in theſe Papers.</p>
            <p>Whereupon, about the end of <hi>February 1685/6.</hi> I put forth the firſt of theſe three Sheets; wherein I prove from the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Title</hi> preſixt to thoſe very Chapters by the Spirit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that <hi>they are properly a Prophecy of things to come to paſs after St.</hi> John's <hi>receiving the Viſion;</hi> which Dr. <hi>M.</hi> with great earneſtneſs had denied in the <hi>xxiſt</hi> Chapter of his <hi>Paralipomena Prophetica</hi> (a Book which he put forth about <hi>November 1685,</hi> after he had ſeen my Expoſition) but he had never taken notice, that the <hi>SPIRIT</hi> himſelf has ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly entitled it <hi>a Viſion of future things,</hi> which was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb facs="tcp:29464:3"/>a very great Overſight in the Doctor. So I thought that my putting him in mind of this, would eaſily put an end to the Diſpute between us; there being nothing to be ſaid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſo plain a Demonſtration. And indeed my Expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on did not fail me, for from that time to this, I have never had a word of Anſwer from him; which, in effect, was yielding up the whole to me, that I contend for in theſe Papers. For if thoſe Chapters be <hi>A Prophecy of things to come to paſs after St.</hi> John's <hi>receiving of the Viſion,</hi> they were not ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paſt, or preſent, at that time. And conſequently, the <hi>Opening</hi> of the ſealed Book, which St. <hi>John</hi> then ſaw, muſt be a Type of the <hi>explaining</hi> of it afterwards (for it prefigures that moſt naturally, and can prefigure nothing elſe) and alſo the <hi>Throne</hi> which he ſaw at the ſame time, muſt needs be a Throne of God which was <hi>afterwards</hi> to be on <hi>Earth,</hi> and cannot ſignify his Throne in the higheſt <hi>Heaven,</hi> which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſted before all Ages. Altho to make all as ſure as I could, I have prov'd theſe things by many other Arguments in theſe Papers. It is therefore highly to be preſum'd that the Doctor would in all this time have defended his Book againſt that firſt attempt of mine, if it had been poſſible; but ſince he has not done it, we may well conclude, that as his Modeſty would not ſuffer him to <hi>confeſs</hi> his Error, otherwiſe than by Silence, ſo it would much leſs allow him to engage in <hi>defence</hi> of it. I lately hear, that ſince (<hi>viz.</hi> in <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt) God has taken him to his Mercy; and let his Memory be ever precious. I hope it will be no Offence to thoſe that have a juſt eſteem for it, if, before I publiſh my ſaid Expoſition to the World, I undertake to clear thoſe Points in difference between us, upon which I am to lay ſo great a ſtreſs; and which if I am not able to make good, it would be vain to meddle any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this buſineſs.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>June vii. 1688.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="question">
            <pb facs="tcp:29464:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> VINDICATION <hi>of certain Papers (not yet made publick) concerning the Expoſition of the fourth and fifth Chapters of the</hi> Revelation, <hi>(the right underſtanding of which Chapters would be of the greateſt advantage to the Church:) from the Exceptions of the Reverend and Learned Dr.</hi> H. M.</head>
            <p>THere is no Viſion in the whole Book of the <hi>Revelation</hi> that has been leſs underſtood hitherto, than that of the <hi>4th</hi> and <hi>5th</hi> Chapters; and yet there is none has been expounded with more eaſe to thoſe that have undertaken that Task, than thoſe Chapters have. For tho there be many Objections both very weighty, and very obvious, to be made againſt the Expoſitions of every one of them (for they all agree as to the main, in a literal kind of way of interpreting them (ſuch as any Child that is but juſt come to the uſe of Reaſon, would be apt at firſt ſight to pitch upon) concurring unanimouſly in one grand miſtake, That by the Lamb's coming and taking the Book out of the hand of him that ſat on the Throne, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7. is repreſented God's giving his Son the Revelation; tho there be many Objections, I ſay, both weighty and obvious, to be alledg'd againſt this way of expounding, yet no Man, tho never ſo learned, ingenious, or curious in theſe Speculations, has ſo much as mention'd one of them, till the learned and ingenious Dr. <hi>M.</hi> being urg'd by ſome Papers I ſent him a while ago, has been pleas'd both to inſert the Objections into his <hi>Paralipomena Prophetica,</hi> Chap. xxxiv. and to give us his Solutions of them. It is a glorious Viſion, as any one may ſee by the bare letter of it; which made me, while I look'd upon it only by the Light which I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd from others, never to read it over without a Sigh. For I could perceive nothing from their Expoſitions, but what is deliver'd much more plainly in other Scriptures: and I could not by any
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:29464:4"/>means perſwade my ſelf that ſo magnificent a Viſion as this is, was written only to inform us, how obſcurely and myſteriouſly common Truths, well kown before, plain, eaſy, and familiar, might be repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented.</p>
            <p>I hope no Man will be ſo uncharitable as to interpret the deſign of what I have here ſaid, to be as if I meant to diſparage other Interpreters, to moſt of whom for any commendable Quality I am no way comparable. For as I honour every Man that with ſo much as but a good intent has ſeem'd to have beſtowed his pains in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicating theſe Myſteries: ſo I ingenuouſly profeſs that nothing but the love of Truth has mov'd me to lay open the ſeeming Inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtencies of their Expoſition. In order to the manifeſting of which Truth, when it ſhall be thought fit by thoſe that are the Judges of what is fit in ſuch caſes; I ſhall now only endeavour to prepare the way, by ſhewing that which the Reverend and Learned Dr. <hi>M.</hi> is forced to deny at any rate, as being utterly inconſiſtent with his own and the common Hypotheſis, <hi>viz. That the Viſion of the fourth and fifth Chapters of the Revelation is properly a Prophecy; and conſequently, that the deſign of the fifth Chapter is not to repreſent God's giving to his Son the Revelation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the fourth and fifth Chapters of the</hi> Revelation <hi>are a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy.</hi> This appears ſo plainly from the Preface that the Spirit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf has prefixt to them, that one would think it impoſſible for any Man to be miſtaken in this Point. <hi>After this I looked</hi> (ſays St. <hi>John,</hi> Chap. iv. 1.) <hi>and behold a Door was opened in Heaven; And the firſt Voice which I heard was as it were of a Trumpet talking with me, ſaying, Come up hither, and I will ſhew thee things which muſt be hereafter.</hi> Is not this as plain an Indication as can be deſired, that the things which St. <hi>John</hi> was now about to ſee, were things to come; and conſequently, that the ſeeing of thoſe things is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſying? But what were thoſe things which the Voice ſhewed him? What can they be, if not thoſe which immediately follow, of which St. <hi>John</hi> gives this Relation, ver. 2, 3, &amp;c. <hi>And immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I was in the Spirit, and behold, a Throne was ſet in Heaven; and one ſat on the Throne, &amp;c. And round about the Throne were four and twenty Elders ſitting,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and out of the Throne proceeded Lightnings, and Thundrings, and Voices; And there were ſeven Lamps of Fire burning before the Throne,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And in the midſt of the Throne, and round about the Throne were four Beaſts, &amp;c.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:29464:4"/>who reſt not day and night, ſaying, Holy, Holy Holy, &amp;c.</hi> And when thoſe Beaſts magnify him that ſate on the Throne, the four and twenty Elders with profound humility give God the Glory of the Works of his Creation. Then in the fifth Chapter he proceeds to tell us how that the <hi>Sitter on the Throne had a Book in his right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, written within, and on the back-ſide, ſealed with ſeven Seals.</hi> Whereupon <hi>a ſtrong Angel</hi> is ſeen <hi>proclaiming with a loud Voice, Who is worthy to open the Book? &amp;c.</hi> verſ. 1, 2. <hi>None in the whole World is found worthy,</hi> verſ. 3. Wherefore St. <hi>John weeps,</hi> ver. 4. <hi>One of the Elders comforts him,</hi> ver. 5. Whereupon St. <hi>John</hi> eſpies <hi>in the midſt of the Throne a Lamb ſtanding as if it had been ſlain, &amp;c.</hi> ver. 6. who <hi>came and took the Book out of the right-hand of him that ſate on the Throne,</hi> ver. 7. Upon which the ſaid <hi>Beaſts and Elders fall down before the Lamb, and ſing a Song</hi> to him, congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulating his taking the Book, and opening the Seals, ver. 8, 9, 10. Then the Prophet hears the Voice of <hi>many Angels round about the Throne, and the Beaſts, and the Elders applauding the Lamb,</hi> ver. 11, 12. And next he hears no leſs than <hi>every Creature in Heaven, Earth, Sea, and under the Earth, giving Bleſſing, Honour, Glory and Power to him that ſitteth on the Throne, and to the Lamb.</hi> The <hi>four Beaſts</hi> ſaying <hi>Amen;</hi> and the <hi>Elders</hi> doing moſt profound reverence alſo, <hi>ver.</hi> 12, 13. — Then he proceeds in Chap. vi. 1, 2, &amp;c. to tell us what he ſaw in the Book when the Lamb had opened it. <hi>And I ſaw</hi> (ſays St. <hi>John) when the Lamb opened one of the Seals, and I heard as it were the noiſe of Thunder; one of the four Beaſts ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Come and ſee. And I ſaw, and behold a white Horſe, and he that ſat on him had a Bow,</hi> &amp;c. And in like manner he goes on, deſcribing what he ſaw at the opening of each Sea. — Now the thing which I affirm is this, That whether the things which St. <hi>John</hi> ſaw in the Book, be a Prophecy of future things or not; yet it muſt needs be that the many other things which he ſaw and heard before the opening of the Book, are a Prophecy. The reaſon is plain; becauſe thoſe words of the Voice [Chap. 4.1. <hi>I will ſhew thee things that muſt be hereafter</hi>] do moſt plainly and immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affect the things which he ſaw in the fourth and fifth Chapters; but not thoſe things which he ſaw in the Book, Chap. 6. Nor does this only appear from the order of Narration, but alſo from the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and nature of the the thing it ſelf. For thoſe words of the Voice [<hi>Come up hither, and I will ſhew thee things that muſt be
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:29464:5"/>hereafter</hi>] muſt neceſſarily refer to the things which the <hi>Voice</hi> ſhew'd him, <hi>viz.</hi> thoſe things which he ſaw by virtue of his being call'd up into Heaven; which things are plainly <hi>the Throne,</hi> with <hi>the Sitter on it,</hi> together with the other things afore-ſpoken of. But as for the things that were contained in the <hi>Book,</hi> he was not ſhew'd them by the <hi>Voice,</hi> but by the <hi>Lamb</hi> that opened the Book, and the <hi>Beaſts</hi> that called him to ſee them; as appears moſt evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.1, 2, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Beſides, the Title of [<hi>things that muſt be hereafter</hi>] is not ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate to the Viſions of the ſealed Book; whoſe Events (even ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Dr. <hi>M</hi>'s own Expoſition) begin as ſoon as thoſe of the Epiſtolar Prophecy. As therefore the Title to the Epiſtolar Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is [<hi>things that are, and things that muſt be hereafter,</hi> Rev. 1.19.] becauſe, as the Doctor truly affirms, the Epiſtles concern the ſtate of the Church then preſent, as well as that which was to come; why ſhould not the Prophecy of the ſealed Book have the ſame Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, ſince the reaſon in all points is the ſame? So plain is it every way, that thoſe words of the Voice <hi>[Come up hither, and I will ſhew thee things which muſt be hereafter]</hi> reſpect not the Viſions of the Book, Chap. 6. but thoſe that immediately follow the ſaid words in Chap. 4.2, 3, <hi>&amp;c. viz.</hi> the Viſion of the Throne, and the reſt that follow.</p>
            <p>If therefore the Viſion of the <hi>Throne,</hi> with the <hi>Sitter on it,</hi> the <hi>Elders</hi> and <hi>Beaſts</hi> praiſing him, the <hi>Book</hi> in the Sitter's Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, the <hi>ſtrong Angels proclaiming,</hi> &amp;c. I ſay, if theſe things be not ſome of thoſe which the Voice points at, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 1. telling the Prophet he would ſhew him <hi>things that muſt come to paſs hereafter,</hi> it will be impoſſible to prove that any part of the <hi>Revelation</hi> is a Prophecy. <hi>Come up hither</hi> (ſays the Voice) <hi>and I will ſhew thee things that muſt be hereafter. And immediately</hi> (ſays the Prophet) <hi>I was in the Spirit, and ſaw</hi> ſuch and ſuch things. And are not they the things then which the Voice ſaid he would ſhew him? Which things, ſince the Voice ſays they are future things, or <hi>things that muſt be hereafter;</hi> it is plain the Viſion of them is a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding this mighty Evidence of Truth, the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Dr. <hi>M.</hi> is pleaſed to expreſs his <hi>Wonder</hi> (in his <hi>Paralipomena Prophetica,</hi> Chap. xxi.) <hi>that any Man of Wit, and Parts, and Learning ſhould be ſo heedleſs and groſly miſtaken, as to make it a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:29464:5"/>Prophecy properly ſo called,</hi> &amp;c. Whereas he that has but the leaſt judgment in the World, muſt needs ſee (if he will not wilfully wink) that the Spirit himſelf ſtiles it a Viſion of <hi>things to come:</hi> And therefore if the Spirit ſpeaks <hi>properly,</hi> the Viſion is <hi>properly a Prophecy.</hi> But let us hear what that Learned Perſon urges in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of his own Opinion. Now the ſubſtance of what he alledges in the ſaid Chapter is this: <q>That the Viſion of the fourth and fifth Chapters of the <hi>Revelation</hi> is no more a Prophecy, than that in <hi>Ezekiel</hi> the firſt; to which alſo it is very like in many reſpects: as that of <hi>Ezekiel</hi> is to the glorious Repreſentation of the God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> made to <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Elders in the Mount, <hi>Exod.</hi> xxiv. wherefore as neither that which <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> or <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaw, was a Prophecy: So neither is it likely that that which St. <hi>John</hi> ſaw is a Prophecy. It is only, or chiefly intended for an <hi>Introductory Viſion</hi> to the Prophecy of the ſealed Book, which begins Chap. 6.1. (a thing uſual with the Prophets, as may be ſeen <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.1, 2. &amp;c. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 1. <hi>Daniel.</hi> 10.5, &amp;c.) and no more a Prophecy than thoſe in <hi>Iſaiah, Ezekiel,</hi> or <hi>Daniel</hi> are, intimating the Divine Inſpiration of <hi>John</hi> in writing thoſe Prophecies, and ſetting forth that in pompous and magnificent Expreſſions, which is noted in a more vulgar ſtile, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.1. <hi>viz.</hi> That God gave his Son the Revelation.</q> To this I anſwer; It is here taken for granted that the Viſion which <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſaw in the places afore-cited, is not a Prophecy; which ought to be clearly proved before any ſtreſs can be laid upon it. But ſuppoſe it to be no Prophecy (for I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſpare time for cavilling) will it thence follow that the Viſion of <hi>Rev.</hi> iv. &amp; v. is no Prophecy, only becauſe in ſome things it agrees with that Viſion of <hi>Ezekiel, i. e.</hi> it ſeems to borrow ſome of its Types from thence? Are not all Interpereters generally agreed, that the Types in the <hi>Revelation</hi> are moſtly borrowed from Stories, Rites, and Conſtitutions of the Jewiſh Church, and taken out of the Old Teſtament, as well the Hiſtorical as Prophetical Parts of it, and yet no Man denies it to be a Prophecy? For Example, do not both Mr. <hi>Mede,</hi> and your ſelf alſo in ſeveral Particulars reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Prophecy of the Woman, <hi>Rev.</hi> xii. 1, &amp;c. to the Hiſtory of the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and coming out of it, <hi>Exod.</hi> i. and in the following Chapter? And yet you never doubt of its being a Prophecy ere the more for that.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:29464:6"/>
            <p>But further, There is a vaſt difference between the Viſion of <hi>Ezekiel</hi> and <hi>Moſes,</hi> and that of St. <hi>John, Rev.</hi> iv. &amp; v. in that this latter is entitled by the Spirit himſelf, [a Vision] <hi>of things that muſt be hereafter.</hi> Now if theſe, or the like words be not prefix'd to that Viſion of <hi>Ezekiel, Moſes,</hi> or that of <hi>Daniel</hi> either afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, how can it be thought good reaſoning, to ſay, thoſe Viſions are no Prophecies, therefore this is none?</p>
            <p>I expected the Doctor ſhould have clear'd this point, (<hi>viz.</hi> the Argument hitherto inſiſted on from thoſe obvious words, <hi>Come up hither, and I will ſhew thee things that muſt be hereafter;</hi> which are the moſt appoſite in the World to prove the Viſion immediately ſubſequent, to be a Prophecy) but I find not the leaſt notice taken of it.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the Doctor inſiſts much upon its being an <hi>Introducto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Viſion</hi> to thoſe of the ſealed Book; as if it could be no Prophecy, if it were an Introductory Viſion.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, by granting it to be an Introductory Viſion indeed; but no otherwiſe Introductory, than the Prophecy of the Sealed-Book introduces that of the Trumpets, <hi>Chap.</hi> viii. or than that does the Prophecy of the Opened-Book (as the Doctor loves to call it) <hi>Chap.</hi> xi. 1, &amp;c. Or than the Viſion of the Vials, <hi>Chap.</hi> xvi. intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces that of the Beaſt, <hi>Chap.</hi> xvii. As one <hi>Hiſtory</hi> may introduce another; ſo one <hi>Prophecy</hi> may introduce another; What ſhould hinder? But now, If by an <hi>Introductory Viſion</hi> be meant a <hi>Preface;</hi> there is no other ſuch as I ſee, than that of Chap. iv. 1. where the Voice calls St. <hi>John</hi> to him, ſaying, <hi>Come up hither, and I will ſhew thee things that muſt be hereafter.</hi> This I ſay is all the <hi>Preface</hi> that I can find; for in the very next Verſe begins an account of the things themſelves, which the Voice promis'd to ſhew him; <hi>viz.</hi> a Prophetical Repreſentation of a glorious Church, with a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Deſcription (in the likeneſs of an Hiſtory) of the Beginning, Progreſs, and Accompliſhment of the Opening of a certain Book, whoſe Contents are particularly deſcribed, Chap. vi. and thoſe that follow. So that here is <hi>Prophetia in Prophetiâ, i. e.</hi> the Prophecy of the <hi>Book</hi> it ſelf, contained in the Prophetical Relation of the <hi>opening</hi> of it. As if it had been ſaid thus: Hereafter ſhall ariſe a Church like that deſcribed <hi>Rev.</hi> iv. wherein a certain Book ſhall be open'd by the Lamb, in ſuch manner and circumſtances as are deſcribed, Chap. v. containing ſuch and ſuch things as are ſaid to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:29464:6"/>have been ſeen in it in the ſixth and following Chapters. Now in ſuch manner of ſpeech as this, who does not ſee that the Deſcription of the Church, and the manner of opening the Book is <hi>introductory</hi> of the things contained in the Book; and yet is as properly a Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, as that contained in the Book is? To which Prophetical Hiſtory of the opening of this Book, thoſe words, <hi>[Come up hither, and I will ſhew thee things that muſt be hereafter</hi> is the only Preface. By which, and by his adding immediately after, that <hi>he was imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately in the Spirit,</hi> upon the ſpeaking of theſe words to him; St. <hi>John</hi>'s Divine Inſpiration in writing this Prophecy, is ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intimated.</p>
            <p>But whereas the Learned Doctor further aſſerts, That the fifth Chapter is added, <hi>for the ſetting forth of that in more pompous and magnificent Expreſſions, which is done but in a vulgar ſtile,</hi> Rev. i. 1. that <hi>God gave his Son the Revelation:</hi> this being a Stone that moſt Interpreters have ſtumbled at, I endeavoured to remove it by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding ſeveral things, the attentive Conſideration of which would give great light to this whole matter in diſpute. And the Doctor has done me the honour to ſet down the Queries themſelves, as he had them from me in Manuſcript, with his Anſwers to them, in the 34th Chapter of his <hi>Paralipomena.</hi> Which Anſwers, tho I am not at all ſatisfied with, unleſs it be that I am much the more confirm'd by them in my former Opinion: Yet I ſhall not here beſtow that needleſs pains of ſhewing the inſufficiency of them. For ſo long as that Aſſertion ſtands good, which I have been hitherto proving, <hi>viz.</hi> That the fourth and fifth Chapters of the <hi>Revelation</hi> are a Prophecy of things to come to paſs <hi>hereafter,</hi> it cannot be that they ſhould be taken up in ſetting forth God's giving to his Son the <hi>Revelation;</hi> which was done <hi>before.</hi> Notwithſtanding, Sir, if you do not think that I have clear'd this Point ſufficiently yet; if you deſire it, I will make it my next buſineſs, God willing, to give you all the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction I can, by ſhewing one by one that my Queries, or Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, do ſtill remain in their full force, notwithſtanding all that you have ſaid to them. But I would not willingly engage ſo deep againſt a Perſon, for whom I have ſo ſingular an eſteem. And as for that which I have here ventur'd upon, I deſire your Pardon, with your moſt candid and charitable Interpretation of it.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="question">
            <pb facs="tcp:29464:7"/>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:29464:7"/>
            <head>II. <hi>That by opening the ſealed Book,</hi> Rev. v. <hi>is meant</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining it. <hi>And that by the</hi> Throne <hi>there, is meant a Throne of God on</hi> Earth, <hi>and not in the higheſt</hi> Heaven.</head>
            <p>HAving prov'd in the former Sheet, That the Viſion of the fourth and fifth Chapters of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> is properly a Prophecy of things that were to come to paſs after the exhibiting of it to St. <hi>John</hi> (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding what has been alledg'd to the contrary by the Learned Dr. <hi>H. M.</hi>) I proceed now to ſhew, concerning the other Points in diſpute between us,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That by that Phraſe of opening the ſealed Book, ſo often us'd <hi>Rev.</hi> v. is meant or prefigur'd the explaining of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That by the Throne, <hi>Rev.</hi> iv. 2, &amp;c. is prefigur'd ſome Throne of God on Earth, and not his Throne in the higheſt Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That by opening the Sealed Book is meant, or prefigur'd the explaining of it. For the truth of this Propoſition, I appealed to the conſtant and unqueſtionable uſe of that Phraſe of opening a Sealed Book, where-ever it occurs throughout the Scripture. As <hi>Dan.</hi> ix. 24. <hi>Seal up the Viſion</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> that it be not opened) and xii. 4. <hi>Seal the Book even to the time of the end.</hi> Alſo by the ſealed Book, <hi>Iſa.</hi> xxix. 11. is meant a Book which no Man could open, or underſtand. Alſo that opening of Prophecies ſignifies explaining them, appears from <hi>Luke</hi> xxiv. 32. where Chriſt is ſaid to have opened the Scriptures; and <hi>Acts</hi> xvii. 3. St. <hi>Paul</hi> is ſaid to have opened and alledg'd (<hi>viz.</hi> out of the Prophecies of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) that Chriſt muſt needs have ſuffer'd. Whence the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is plain, That if by Sealing a Prophecy be conſtantly meant in Scripture concealing the Senſe of it, ſo that altho it be written, and in every Man's Hand, yet none knows what it means; and if on the other ſide, by opening a Prophecy conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd as ſealed or myſterious, be conſtantly meant explaining it; it is all the reaſon in the World, that it ſhould be ſo expounded
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29464:8"/>in the place we are upon, as it is in all other places.</p>
            <p>To this the Doctor anſwers in the xxxiii Chap. of his <hi>Par. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetica,</hi> by diſtinguiſhing between opening a Book, and opening a Text. To open a Book, is to unclaſp it; to open the Text, is to explain it. And thus it is one thing to open a ſealed Book where the Prophecy is, and another to open a ſealed Prophecy; which is evident from <hi>Luke</hi> iv. 17. where <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſometimes ſignifies to explain, ſignifies only to open a Book of Prophecies, or to expoſe the Writing to view; which, ſays the Doctor, is the caſe here of the ſeven-ſealed Book, as appears from <hi>Rev.</hi> vi. where the opening of the Seals is exemplified, and the meaning ſhew'd to be only the exhibiting to <hi>John</hi> ſo many particular Viſions, but not the explaining of thoſe Viſions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply</hi> 1. The Lamb is ſaid <hi>Rev.</hi> vi. not barely to have opened the Book, but to have opened the Seals of it. Now the Seals of a Book are always upon the Text; for we no where read of a Book ſealed any otherwiſe than in reſpect to the myſteriouſneſs of it. The Seals of a Book are not ſuch as may be broken with the Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, or cut off with a Knife, or mall'd with an Hammer (if the ſeven Epiſtles indeed had been ſaid to have been ſealed, we might have had more reaſon to have fancied them ſuch) but which yield only to the judgment and underſtanding of the pious Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, through the aſſiſtance of the Spirit of God. And this the Doctor grants, while he ſhews himſelf very willing, but as little able, to produce one inſtance to the contrary. But now if the Seals be always upon the Text, then the Lamb's opening of the Seals in the Viſion, muſt needs figure the opening of the Text, which the Doctor grants to be explaining the ſenſe of it. And (ſince I have before proved the Viſion to be a Prophecy) it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears from hence that it is a Prophecy concerning the explaining of the ſealed Book; in which the Lamb opening the Seals to St. <hi>John,</hi> and ſhewing him the inſide Writing, is a Type of Chriſt, or of his Church, that ſhould afterwards explain the meaning of it to the Faithful. 2. The Doctor in his <hi>Apoc. Apocalypſeos</hi> on <hi>Rev.</hi> v. 1. grants the Seals of the Book to ſignify its <hi>Arcana;</hi> and whereas the Book is ſaid to have been written within and on the back-ſide, the Doctor there expounds the inſide Writing to be the <hi>inward Senſe</hi> of the Book, in oppoſition to the literal ſenſe, which is the back-ſide writing. Whence it muſt undeniably follow, That to open the Seals of the Book, ſo that the inſide-writing may be ſeen, is to ſhew the inward ſenſe of it; or, which is all one, to explain it.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:29464:8"/>
            <p>Wherefore as to what the Doctor ſays of the Lamb's opening the Seals <hi>Rev.</hi> vi. that it is only the exhibiting certain Viſions to St. <hi>John,</hi> but not explaining them (from whence he peremptorily concludes, that whatever in other places may be meant by opening the Seals of a Book, it cannot be underſtood here of explaining it); I anſwer, The Doctor to maintain a literal ſenſe of this Phraſe of opening a ſealed Book (the ſenſe which he is ſo zealous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt in other caſes) is pleas'd to make himſelf extremely igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in a point of ordinary cognizance. For why, I beſeech you, Sir, may not Chriſt's explaining the inward ſenſe of this Book at ſome time or other to his Servants, be fore-ſignified by the Lamb's opening the Seals of it in the Viſion and ſhewing the inſide-writing of it to St. <hi>John?</hi> The Doctor grants the Lamb to repreſent Chriſt; St. <hi>John</hi> to repreſent the People of God (upon <hi>Rev.</hi> v. 4.) he grants the inſide-writing of the Book to ſignify the inward ſenſe of it (in the place a little afore quoted.) What is it then that he denies? Why, tho he grants all this ſingly, yet he denies, when put together, that the Lamb's opening the Seals and ſhewing the inſide-writing to St. <hi>John,</hi> ſignifies Chriſt's explaining at ſome time or other to his People the inward Senſe of the Book. Which, how unreaſonable a thing it is, I leave to the judgment of any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Reader.</p>
            <p>It is therefore to me one of the greateſt Wonders in the World, that the Doctor who cries up the <hi>Apocalyps for a Book ſo throughly ſymbolical,</hi> that he will by no means allow <hi>Hail-ſtones or Earthquakes to be interpreted literally</hi> (See <hi>Par, Proph.</hi> Chap. xlviii. p. 444.) ſhould be here ſo ſtiff for the literal ſenſe of opening the Seals of a Prophetick Book, which (as God would have it) has no literal ſenſe at all. But certainly one would be ſurpriz'd, who has heard to what a degree the Doctor both derides and pities <hi>R.H.</hi> of <hi>Salis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> (Epilogue to <hi>Apoc. Apocalypſeos,</hi> p. 297.) for doting on the literal ſenſe of the <hi>Apocalypſe,</hi> to ſind him caught in the ſame ſnare himſelf, and become as zealous an <hi>R. H—ian</hi> as the Gentleman he oppos'd, even in a Type or Symbol which is never known to have been us'd in ſuch a ſenſe. For a further Confirmation of the Senſe of which Phraſe, I will inſtance but in one plain caſe, which we have <hi>Dan.</hi> xii. 4. where the Prophet is commanded to ſeal the Book even to the time of the end. For if opening the Seals of a Book be no more than expoſing, the bare words (without ſenſe) to view; how can the Book of <hi>Daniel</hi> be ſaid to have been ſealed to the time of the end, when the words of it have been viſible from
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29464:9"/>the time of his receiving them? If you ſay, That opening the Seals of a Book may ſignify only expoſing the bare words tho not in that place of <hi>Daniel:</hi> I deſire but what is very fair, That you would ſhew me then ſome other place, where the Phraſe ſignifies what you contend; or elſe confeſs that you have err'd about it.</p>
            <p>But if it could be ſhew'd (which I believe can never be) that opening the Seals of a Book is ſomewhere found to have a literal ſenſe; yet ſuch a ſenſe not only would be diſſonant from the ſtile and genius of the <hi>Apocalypſe,</hi> but in the Viſion we are now upon, impoſſible to be true. For in the literal ſenſe the Seals were open'd by the Lamb in the preſence of St. <hi>John</hi> 1600 Years ago, at the time of his ſeeing this Viſion; whereas I have before manifeſtly proved this Viſion to be a Prophecy of things that were to come to paſs after. From whence it follows that the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations made to St. <hi>John</hi> in it, (whereof that of opening the ſealed Book is the moſt inſiſted on of any) are meerly ſymbolical, and to be conſider'd only as Images of thoſe future things.</p>
            <p>Moreover there are two other things which make the literal ſenſe of the Seals open'd in St. <hi>John</hi>'s time impoſſible. One is, That no ſuch loud Proclamation was ever heard before that open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as is expreſly ſaid to have been made before the true opening of them, <hi>Rev.</hi> v. 2. <hi>I ſaw</hi> (ſays the Prophet) <hi>a ſtrong Angel pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming with a loud voice; Who is worthy to open the Book, and to looſe the Seals of it?</hi> And this Proclamation is repreſented as made in the hearing of all the World, as plainly appears from the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn given in upon it in the next Verſe, <hi>viz.</hi> That no Man in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, in Earth, or under the Earth, was able to open the Book, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whence we may certainly conclude, that if no Man living in St. <hi>John</hi>'s time did ever hear any ſuch Proclamation made, then was not that which is meant by opening of the Seals, tranſacted in St. <hi>John</hi>'s time. For it ſeems very abſurd to infer that no Man was able to open the Book, becauſe upon loud (or publick) Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation made, no Man appear'd to do it, if no Man then in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ever heard the Proclamation.</p>
            <p>To this Dr. <hi>M.</hi> anſwers, That the Proclamation was never made but only in Viſion (<hi>Par. Proph.</hi> Chap. xxxiv. <hi>Reſp. ad prim.</hi>) And he there alſo gives this reaſon why it was not needful to be fulfill'd, becauſe the Viſion is Dramatical, <hi>i. e.</hi> in the nature of a Stage-play. And he explains his Sentiments of the Viſion yet more clearly Chap. xxi. <hi>p.</hi> 189. <hi>lin.</hi> 19. where ſpeaking with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Viſion in <hi>Rev.</hi> iv, &amp; v. he tells us that it is the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:29464:9"/>of the Angelical Kingdom that they can exhibit Prophetical Shows or Plays, when we Mortals can exhibit only Hiſtorical Ones. So that according to this account, the ivth and vth Chapters of the <hi>Revelation</hi> are a Play or Show exhibited by the Angelical Kingdom; and for that reaſon there needs be no completion of them.</p>
            <p>To this I reply, 1. That I have prov'd thoſe Chapters to be as much a Prophecy, as any part of the <hi>Revelation</hi> can be prov'd to be, and that from the clear Teſtimony of the Spirit himſelf, who has prefix'd the Title of <hi>Things that muſt be hereafter</hi> to them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If <hi>Rev.</hi> iv, &amp; v. be a Play that was really acted in Heaven; I deſire to be inform'd, 1. Who acted the Sitter on the Throne, and the ſlain Lamb, which are the chief Parts in it. The Doctor tells us (<hi>Par. Proph.</hi> Chap. xxxiv. about the beginning) that by the Sitter on the Throne is meant God, and by the ſlain Lamb, Chriſt Jeſus. But it were abſurd to ſay, either that they act Plays, or that any Creature acts their Parts. Therefore the Viſion is not Dramatical. 2. It is manifeſt that thoſe under the Earth (by whom the Doctor on the place underſtands Wizards, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) have a part in this Play too, as may be ſeen <hi>Rev.</hi> v. 3, 13. But none of the Angels in Heaven could have ſuch a part put upon them, therefore the Viſion is not a Play acted by Angels, but like other Viſions prefigurative of things to come.</p>
            <p>But now as to the reaſon why, there needs be no completion of this Viſion, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe it is Dramatical; this is ſo far from being a reaſon of it, that (if it were true) it would be a good reaſon for the quite contrary. For, 1. How can this be a Prophetical Show or Play (as the Doctor calls it) if it be not to be fulfill'd in ſome real thing to come? 2. It is the nature of all Plays to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent real things; ſo far is it from all reaſon to imagine a Play acted by Angels to be only a Fiction, as the Proclamation we ſpeak of muſt needs be, if it were never made, nor to be made, but only in the Viſion. 3. If the Viſion of the Angel proclaiming, needs not to be punctually fulfill'd, as being a part of a Dramatical Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſince it is certain and confeſt by the Doctor himſelf that the Viſion of the opening the Seals (whereof that of the Angel pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming, is part) reaches to the end of <hi>Rev.</hi> xi. It will follow that from the firſt mention of the opening of the Seals, <hi>Rev.</hi> v. to the end of the whole Relation of it <hi>Rev.</hi> xi. the Viſions are Dramati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal; and therefore need no punctual Completion. So that the Doctor has beſtow'd a great deal of pains to little purpoſe in inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting the Viſions of the Book, <hi>Rev.</hi> vi. when it may be alledg'd,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29464:10"/>that they were exhibited only in a Play or Show, and need no more to be fulfill'd than the Viſion of the ſtrong Angel we are ſpeaking of.</p>
            <p>The other thing which makes the literal ſenſe of opening the Book in St. <hi>John</hi>'s time impoſſible to be the ultimate ſenſe of that Phraſe, is that which is ſaid <hi>Rev.</hi> v. 13. where St. <hi>John</hi> ſays he heard every Creature in Heaven, in Earth, in the Sea, and under the Earth, ſaying, <hi>Bleſſing, and Glory, and Honour, and Power be unto him that ſitteth upon the Throne, and to the Lamb for ever and ever.</hi> In which Hymn ſince every Creature was to be concern'd; if it had been ſaid in St. <hi>John</hi>'s time, we ſhould certainly have had ſome footſteps of it in Hiſtory. But there is no ſuch Paſſage any where to be found, and yet it was to be before the Lamb's opening of the Seals, as plainly appears from the uninterrupted order of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, <hi>Rev.</hi> v. 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Therefore the true opening of the Seals was not in St. <hi>John</hi>'s time.</p>
            <p>To this the Doctor anſwers as ſtrangely as to the former (<hi>Par. Proph.</hi> Chap. xxxiv. <hi>Reſp. ad</hi> 10.) not reſolving whether it was to have any Completion, or not, as being Dramatical too; but if it ought to be fulfill'd at all, he ſays it is not to be till the <hi>Millenni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> as neither that before it at <hi>ver.</hi> 9, 10. where the Beaſts and Elders ſay, they ſhall reign upon the Earth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply</hi> 1. The Text it ſelf ſays, That that Hymn of the Beaſts and Elders was ſung upon the Lamb's taking of the Book (which Dr. <hi>M.</hi> makes to be in St. <hi>John</hi>'s time) <hi>Rev.</hi> v. 8. <hi>And when the Lamb had taken the Book, they ſung,</hi> &amp;c. according to which account it ſhould have been paſt theſe 1600 Years. Likewiſe the Hymn ſounded forth by <hi>every Creature</hi> is put before the Lamb's opening any one of the Seals, as is evident to any one that reads. And is it not very ſtrange that in the ſame uninterrupted Series of Relation, the Lamb's taking the Book <hi>Rev.</hi> v. 7. ſhould have been done 1600 Years ago, but that the Song ſaid in the next Verſe to have been ſung thereupon, ſhould not be fulfill'd till the <hi>Millen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium,</hi> as neither the Gratulation of the Angels, <hi>ver.</hi> 11, 12. nor the Hymn ſaid by every Creature, <hi>ver.</hi> 13, 14. And that in the very next Verſe, <hi>viz.</hi> Chap. vi. 1. there ſhould be a regreſſion to things paſt 1600 Years ago, as the opening of the Book is ſaid by Dr. <hi>M.</hi> to be? 2. Whereas the Doctor makes it an Argument, that the Song of the Beaſts and Elders, <hi>Chap.</hi> v. 8, 9, 10. ſhall not be fulfill'd till the <hi>Millennium,</hi> becauſe they ſay, they ſhall reign upon the Earth; it is plain from thoſe words, <hi>ſhall reign,</hi> that their Reign
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:29464:10"/>was not then begun; and conſequently, that the Hymn was to be ſung before the <hi>Millennium.</hi> 3. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>octor himſelf on <hi>Rev.</hi> xi. 16. makes theſe Elders to be our noble Reformers, who are already dead and gone. Alſo upon <hi>Rov.</hi> xv. 7, &amp;c. he expounds the ſeven Angels (to whom one of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Beaſts is ſaid there to give ſeven Vials) to be half path <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Wherefore the Beaſt that gave them their Vials muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſomething before the <hi>Millennium,</hi> which is not yet come. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow arbitrary is it, to make in the ſame Viſion, the Beaſts and Elders, <hi>Chap.</hi> v. 8. to ſigure ſomething to come; but the ſtrong Angel proclaiming, <hi>ver.</hi> 2. to figure no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all, (altho in all the Epiſtles, and in many other places, the <hi>Angels</hi> of the Churches are by the current of Interpreters expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Men;</hi> and ought to be ſo in all places of the Prophecy, for ought I ſee yet to the contrary) nor the opening of the Seals to ſigure any thing here, tho it be never us'd but figuratively in any other place? But laſtly, If the Hymn ſaid by every Creature, <hi>Rev.</hi> v. 13. and that by the Beaſts and Elders, <hi>ver.</hi> 9, 10. be not to be ſung till the <hi>Millennium;</hi> it is certain from the unqueſtionable Order of the Relation, that the Seals are not to be open'd till then neither. For <hi>when</hi> (that is, ſoon after) <hi>the Lamb had taken the Book,</hi> that Hymn which was ſung by the Beaſts and Elders, is expreſly ſaid to have been ſung, <hi>ver.</hi> 8. And the Seals were not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened by the Lamb, till he had taken the Book; therefore the opening of the Bock was to be much about the ſame time with the Song ſung by the Beaſts and Elders, and cannot by any means be thought to have been fulfill'd 1600 Years before it. Whence it follows, That that Phraſe of opening the Book cannot be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood literally, <hi>i. e.</hi> it can't be underſtood to ſignify no more, than what was done in the Viſion preſented to St. <hi>John</hi> 1600 Years ago. And thus much to prove that by opening the Sealed Book, <hi>Rev.</hi> v. is meant explaining it.</p>
            <p>As to the other Point, <hi>viz.</hi> That by the Throne in the Viſion I am upon, is meant a Throne of God upon Earth; becauſe I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bring the proof of it within the compaſs of this Sheet of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, I reſerve it to another, if God permit. Tho it may ſeem to be prov'd already, in that, 1. The Throne is plainly one of thoſe things which the Spirit expreſly calls things future, <hi>Rev.</hi> iv. 1, 2, <hi>&amp;c. Come up hither</hi> (ſays the Voice) <hi>and I will ſhew thee things that muſt be hercaſter</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi> things which are not yet in being; much leſs things which have been the ſame from all Eternity.) <hi>And immediately</hi> (ſays the Prophet, as the reſult of the Voice's calling to him) <hi>I was
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:29464:11"/>in the Spirit, and behold, a Throne was ſet in Heaven, and one ſat upon it.</hi> Wherefore ſince it is evident that this Throne was not in being at the time of the exhibiting of this Viſion to St. <hi>John;</hi> what can be more plain, than that it is not the Throne of God in the higheſt Heaven? 2. If by opening the Seals, be meant explaining the Book to the People of God (as I have prov'd it is) then it muſt needs follow, that the Lamb with ſeven Horns and ſeven Eyes, that opens the Book, is not Chriſt himſelf in Perſon, but the Church of Chriſt (as the Lamb, <hi>Rev.</hi> xvii. 14. is expounded, <hi>Rev.</hi> xiii. 7. and even by reaſon it ſelf.) For ſince the time of his converſing with us in the Fleſh, we are not to expect that he ſhould come in Perſon to explain any Book to us. And conſequently the Throne, in the middle of which the Lamb is repreſented, is ſome earthly Throne.</p>
            <div type="corollary">
               <head>A Corollary.</head>
               <p>If by opening the Book, <hi>Rev.</hi> v. be meant explaining it; then moſt certain it is, That the time of the Church prefigur'd in that Chapter, is that wherein the Book we ſpeak of, has been or ſhall be <hi>firſt</hi> explain'd. For whereas it is ſaid, That upon Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made, no Man in the World could explain it, <hi>ver.</hi> 2, 3. and when St. <hi>John</hi> wept becauſe no body was found able, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently thereupon an Elder is repreſented as comforting him with the joyful News of the unfolding of it, in theſe words, <hi>Weep not, Behold, the Lion of the Tribe of</hi> Judah, <hi>the Root of</hi> David <hi>hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed to open the Book,</hi> v. 5. As who ſhould ſay, Behold, through the aſſiſtance of Chriſt, whoſe Merits are ever prevalent with God for the good of his Church, I have ſet forth an Explication of it. Whence it undeniably follows, That the time of the Church preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gur'd in that Chapter, is the very time wherein it would pleaſe that Lion of the Tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> to impart the firſt true Expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that Book to his People. And the Book is the ſame which the Lamb takes, <hi>Chap.</hi> v. 7. and opens, <hi>Chap.</hi> vi. where alſo the Contents of it are particularly rehearſed. If therefore that Book be truly expounded (as no doubt it is) already; then is the time prefigur'd in <hi>Rev.</hi> v. 5. paſt. And the Perſon that has done it (being one of the four and twenty Elders) was a Member of that glorious Church deſcrib'd, <hi>Chap.</hi> iv. 4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So that that Church, or ſtate of the Church, muſt needs be come alſo: which Obſervation will be of great uſe to us, when we come to the particular Explication of the Prophecy.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="question">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:29464:11"/>
            <head>III. <hi>More Arguments to ſhew, That by the</hi> Throne, Rev. iv. &amp; v. <hi>is meant a Throne of God on</hi> Earth, <hi>and not in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt</hi> Heaven. <hi>With Anſwers to Objections.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>TO the two Arguments made uſe of in the former Sheet, to prove that by the Throne, <hi>Rev.</hi> iv, &amp; v. is meant ſome Throne of God on Earth, and not in the higheſt Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; I now add,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That it is certain, and confeſt by all Interpreters, that by Heaven in ſome places of the <hi>Revelation</hi> (as alſo in other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies of Scripture) is meant an Heaven upon Earth. As in <hi>Rev.</hi> xii. where we have mention of a Woman in Heaven, and of a great Red Dragon there alſo perſecuting her (which Dragon is call'd, at <hi>ver.</hi> 9. the Devil and Satan) and the Woman afterwards flying into the Wilderneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Who can be ſo ſenſleſs as to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret this Heaven, otherwiſe than of an Heaven upon Earth, where the Woman (the Church) is perſecuted by her profeſt Enemy the Devil? Since therefore it is ſo demonſtrably certain, that in this Prophecy, Heaven is ſometimes taken for an Heaven upon Earth; and it cannot be made out clearly, that Heaven, where it is ſpoken of as the Scene of any Action, is ever uſed there in any other ſenſe; it follows, that the Heaven we ſpeak of, <hi>Rev.</hi> iv, &amp; v. is an Heaven upon Earth too; and conſequently the Throne there ſpoken of, an Earthly Throne. But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> If it could be made appear, that Heaven, where it is made the Scene of Action, is any where us'd in this Prophecy for the higheſt Heaven: Yet here it were a moſt unreaſonable thing to take it in that ſenſe. For then the Sitter on the Throne, with the Book ſealed in his Right Hand, <hi>Rev.</hi> v. 1. muſt be God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And whereas it is ſaid in the next Verſe, that Proclamation was made by a ſtrong Angel, <hi>Who is worthy to open the Book?</hi> &amp;c. In the 3d Verſe, it is return'd thereupon, <hi>That no Man in Heaven, nor in Earth, neither under the Earth, was able to open the Book, neither to look thereon.</hi> The meaning of which (if by Heaven be meant the higheſt Heaven) muſt be, That Chriſt himſelf was not able
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29464:12"/>to open the Book, neither to look thereon; which were moſt abſurd. And the more, becauſe it is certain, that God had given his Son the Revelation, (whereof the Book we ſpeak of is confeſt to be a part) before ever this Viſion was exhibited to St. <hi>John.</hi> For Chriſt would not have ſent his Angel to ſignify it to his Servant <hi>John, Rev.</hi> i. 1. if God had not ſignified it to Chriſt before. Wherefore when it is ſaid; <hi>That no Man in Heaven was able to open the Book;</hi> the meaning cannot be, that no Man in the higheſt Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, where Chriſt ſitteth at the Right Hand of God, was able; but it muſt be expounded (as it is certain that it ought in other places) of an Heaven upon Earth.</p>
            <p>To this the Doctor anſwers, That Chriſt is excepted; accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as is anſwered by St. <hi>Paul</hi> in a like Caſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> xv. 27. But I reply, That let the Doctor underſtand it how he pleaſes, it is certain that St. <hi>John</hi> did not underſtand it with exception of Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> as if it had been ſaid, No Man in Heaven, but Chriſt, was able to open the Book. And this appears from what follows in the iv. <hi>ver.</hi> where St. <hi>John</hi> tells us, <hi>He wept much, becauſe no Man was found worthy to open and read the Book, neither to look thereon.</hi> For if the Sitter on the Throne were God Almighty on the Throne of Glory, with a Book in his Right Hand ſealed, how odly would it have look'd in St. <hi>John</hi> to weep, and that much, becauſe no Man but Chriſt was found worthy to open it? For whom could he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect or deſire ſhould do it beſides? But the Doctor adds (<hi>Par. Proph. Chap.</hi> xxxiv. <hi>reſp. ad</hi> 5.) That St. <hi>John</hi> did not know as yet, that Chriſt was worthy to open the Book and read it, nor ſo much as to look upon it. <hi>Repl.</hi> I wonder the Doctor ſhould ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to ſay ſo! For this is to make that great Apoſtle, and beloved Diſciple, a very ignorant Man indeed. For did not St. <hi>John</hi> know the Worthineſs and Abilities of Chriſt, as well as any Man? The Prophet had cauſe to weep then indeed, if he were ſo weak as to think that Chriſt himſelf was not worthy to read the Book. But how could he be ignorant of that, which every Chriſtian is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to know? Beſides, St. <hi>John</hi> muſt needs have known what the Book was, or elſe he would not have wept that no Man could open it. But it is confeſt on all hands, that the Book was part of the Revelation. So that St. <hi>John</hi> of all Men could not be ignorant of Chriſt's Worthineſs to open the Book, when he knew that Chriſt had call'd him on purpoſe to communicate it to him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But if St. <hi>John</hi>'s ignorance of Chriſt's Worthineſs had not been the cauſe of his Weeping, how comes the Elder, <hi>ver.</hi> v.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:29464:12"/>to comfort him in theſe words; <hi>Weep not; behold, the Lion of the Tribe of</hi> Judah, <hi>the Root of</hi> David <hi>hath prevailed to open the Book?</hi> &amp;c. For by this it ſhould ſeem that St. <hi>John</hi> did not know that Chriſt could do it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I have before prov'd this Viſion to be a Prophecy, and that by <hi>Opening</hi> the Book, is prefigur'd the <hi>Explaining</hi> of it. So that the meaning of the Elder's words is plainly this: Not that Chriſt in his own Perſon hath given out an Expoſition of the Book, but that ſome Member of his Church on Earth hath done it, through the prevalence of his Interceſſion. As if the Elder had ſaid, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, I, through the Merits of Chriſt, have been enabled to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the Book. So that the true reaſon of St. <hi>John</hi>'s weeping was, becauſe no Man in this World was found at that time worthy to open the Book; and therefore Chriſt is not excepted, becauſe not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, as being not in this World. And thus are thoſe great Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities eaſily avoided, which muſt needs follow upon making the Sitter on the Throne to be God Almighty; and the Heaven here ſpoken of, the higheſt Heaven; which can by no means be allow'd to be the ſenſe of this Prophecy.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Sitter on the Throne appears to be a Man, and not God in his own Perſon, from the deſcription that is given of him, <hi>Rev.</hi> iv. 3. where he is ſaid to be to look on like a Jaſper and a Sardine Stone; whereas God Almighty in his own Perſon, no Man hath ſeen at any time, (1 <hi>Tim.</hi> vi. 16.) nor can ſee. Is it not therefore very abſurd, to imagine the Inviſible God to be deſcrib'd, by telling us what He looks like? But now, if we conceive the Sitter on the Throne to be ſome Repreſentative of God (as a King, or the like) it would be very proper to deſcribe him by the likeneſs of his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance; and to ſay that ſuch an one was to look on like a Jaſper and a Sardine Stone, would be the propereſt Deſcription of any. For as much as ſuch Perſons are wont to appear upon their Thrones in ſuch Ornaments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> That Hymn, <hi>Holy, holy, holy, Lord God Almighty,</hi> &amp;c. cannot be ſung to any Creature, which yet is ſung to the Sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter on the Throne, <hi>Rev.</hi> iv. 8. Alſo the Sitter on the Throne is ſaid <hi>to Live for ever and ever;</hi> and ſuch Worſhip and Adoration is paid to him, as cannot be given to a Creature without Idolatry. To this purpoſe it is Objected by the Doctor, in the xxxiii. Chap. of his <hi>Paralipom. Prophetica.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, It is a miſtake in the Doctor, to ſay that that Hymn, Holy, holy, holy, Lord God Almighty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is ſaid to be directed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:29464:13"/>to the Sitter on the Throne: Whereas the Text it ſelf has only theſe words, <hi>And they reſt not day and night, ſaying,</hi> (without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing to whom 'tis ſaid, leaving us thereby to underſtand that it is ſaid only to the B. Trinity) <hi>Holy, holy, holy,</hi> &amp;c. The next Verſe indeed makes mention of giving Glory to the Sitter on the Throne; but then the words of that Doxology, are only theſe: <hi>Thou art worthy, O Lord, to receive Glory, and Honour, and Power; for thou haſt Created all things, and for thy Pleaſure they are, and were Created,</hi> Rev. iv. 11.</p>
            <p>But is it lawful then to uſe ſuch Expreſſions as theſe to any Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative of God? <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is as lawful to uſe them to a Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative of God, as to uſe them to a God that looks like a Jaſper and a Sardine Stone. For can any thing that in its own Nature and Perſon looks like a Jaſper and a Sardine Stone, be the God that liveth for ever and ever, in a proper literal ſenſe? And there is an improper Analogical Senſe, wherein a King may be ſaid to live for ever and ever, as well as a Man may be call'd Good, or Wiſe, or Holy. For we know our Saviour ſays expreſly, that <hi>there is none good but God;</hi> and yet in a reſerv'd ſenſe, we commonly call Men good too, without any offence or fault at all. The like may be ſaid of calling Men wiſe, and holy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And why may not as well the title of <hi>Living for ever and ever,</hi> be attributed to a King? For it is certain, that there is or ſhall be a Kingdom in this World, that ſhall laſt for ever and ever, <hi>Dan.</hi> ii. 44. &amp; vii. 27. <hi>Rev.</hi> xi. 15. &amp; xxii. 5. And it is as certain, that the ſeveral Kings of any Kingdom ruling ſucceſſively one after another, are repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Prophecy but as one King; as may be ſeen in many places of the viii. Chap. of <hi>Daniel,</hi> and in <hi>Rev.</hi> xvii. 10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and is confeſt by all Interpreters. Whence it follows, that as the Kingdom it ſelf is ſaid to continue for ever, ſo the King of it may as well be ſaid to live for ever; in what ſenſe the one may be ſaid, the other may be ſaid alſo. But here it is to be obſerv'd yet farther, that I do not ſay that the Sitter on the Throne is not God, but that it is not God in his own Perſon, but deſcrib'd according as He is pleas'd to exhibit himſelf glorious in ſome Earthly Prince. As when, with reſpect to his delivering his People out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> God is deſcrib'd as having a mighty Hand, and a ſtretched-out Arm; not that God in his own Perſon has any bodily Parts, but this is ſpoken with reſpect to <hi>Moſes,</hi> whoſe Hand and Arm God made uſe of in that Work, making his Hand Mighty, and the ſtretching-out of his Arm to do Wonders. So that in effect, the Sitter on the Throne is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:29464:13"/>God and the King too, or God working in and by the King, who is here conſider'd only as God's Inſtrument in the Work, for which thanks is given to them both as one, in being given to the Sitter on the Throne. Wherefore the Doxology given to the Sitter on the Throne, (together with the other expreſſions of Devotion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with mentioned) is ſo to be underſtood as being only by Analogy or Myſtery applicable to the Viſible Sitter that look'd like a Jaſper and a Sardine Stone; but properly and literally to God Almighty the Inviſible <hi>Co-ſeſſor</hi> and Director of him.</p>
            <p>But the Doctor further urges in the place afore-quoted, that there is no ground for making two Sitters on the Throne. <hi>Anſw.</hi> If there be ground for making the Sitter on the Throne a good King, there muſt be the ſame for making God to ſit with him, by his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible Aſſiſtance and Direction. So that in making the Sitter on the Throne to be a King directed by God ſitting with him, I make indeed no more than one Sitter on the Throne; according as <hi>One</hi> is taken in the holy Scriptures ſive hundred times, as where we are forbidden to have more Maſters than One, and the like. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, if the Spirit has vouchſafed to ſay of every ordinary Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, that he is one with God and Chriſt: How glorious and indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluble is the Union between God and a good King, whom he vouchſafes to make his Inſtrument in the Delivering or Protecting of his Church? So that the making of God and the King to be the Sitter on the Throne, is ſo far from making two Sitters, that he could not be a good King, unleſs God were ſuppos'd to ſit with him.</p>
            <p>But were it not Idolatry in People to worſhip God by any Viſible Repreſentative of his, ſitting in the midſt of them, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the deſcription in <hi>Rev.</hi> iv. where is one ſitting viſibly in the midſt of the Throne, with four <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (or living Creatures) and twenty four Elders round about him? <hi>Anſw.</hi> As to the Viſion, there can be no Idolatry in that, becauſe it is but a Viſion, and no real thing. And as to the Completion of it, we muſt not think that the Prophecy is to be underſtood in that groſs manner, as if it were never to be fulfill'd, till the Perſons ſignified by the Living Creatures and Elders ſhould get together about a Throne, paying their moſt profound Devotions to one looking like a Jaſper and a Sardine Stone, ſitting in the midſt of it. But the meaning is only to ſhew the Order of the Hierarchy, the Perſon ſitting in the midſt of the Throne, being the Supreme Viſible Governour; the Living Creatures in the midſt of the Throne, and round about the Throne, next under him; and the 24 Elders under them. In which
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:29464:14"/>Order (not Local, but Political) or Subordination one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Inferiours pay their duties to their Superiour, and all of them to that good God, who inviſibly preſides in the midſt of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But the Doxology we ſpeak of, <hi>Rev.</hi> iv. 11. is addreſt to the Sitter on the Throne for his <hi>Creating of all things,</hi> and how then could any Mortal have an hand with him?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In the Language of the Prophets, any notable alteration of Affairs, is call'd a New Creation. And as for the term of <hi>all things,</hi> it is very often ſaid not of
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> obſerve, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> is,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>which the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> know, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> eaſily <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>; as if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>en ſaid,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou haſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all <hi>theſe</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Vid. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> all things Uni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſally, but of thoſe things only which had been the ſubject of the foregoing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. Which Points being confeſt by all Interpreters of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (ſo far as I know) will need no further proof. And thus have I vindicated the Sitter on the Throne to be a Man, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the Throne to be an Earthly Throne. I proceed,</p>
            <p n="6">6. The Throne appears to be an Earthly Throne alſo, by the Company that are gather'd about it. For theſe are call'd <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Living Creatures, and Elders; which are Names we never find given to any but Mortals. And it is a very dangerous thing, for the ſake of an Hypotheſis, and to ſerve a Turn, to depart from the conſtant and unqueſtionable uſe of Words, by affixing private and unwarrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Interpretations to them. Theſe Perſons are alſo prov'd to be Mortals, by the Incenſe they are repreſented with, <hi>Rev.</hi> v. 8. which is a Type of the aſcending up of the Prayers of the Church from Earth to Heaven. From whence Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> upon the place in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, that the Perſons uſing it, are the Church on Earth. And he infers the like from what they ſay of themſelves, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. that they were <hi>made to God Kings and Prieſts, and that they ſhould reign upon the Earth.</hi> For this deſcription can neither agree to Angels, nor to Souls departed. But if the Company about the Throne be Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, the Throne muſt needs be an Earthly Throne. And ſince mention has been made of the Famous and Learned Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> I crave leave to add, That he is ſo far from ſcrupling to interpret the Sitter on the Throne to be a Man, that he makes him not ſo much as a King, but only a Biſhop. For which, ſee his Annotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on <hi>Rev.</hi> iv. 2. and I look upon Dr. <hi>Hammand</hi> to be as good a Judg as any Man of what Interpretations are <hi>ſafe,</hi> tho' not ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways of what are <hi>ſound.</hi> But to return to our purpoſe,</p>
            <p n="7">7. The <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> is a City that was to be on Earth, as appears from <hi>Rev.</hi> xxi. 2. where it is ſaid to come down from God out of Heaven. The ſame is ſaid of it again at <hi>ver.</hi> 10. where alſo St. <hi>John</hi> is carried up but to an high Mountain to ſee it; ſo that it muſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:29464:14"/>needs be an Earthly City: And if it came down from God out of Heaven (as is ſaid of it) whither could it come but to the Earth? Accordingly we find it ſaid at <hi>ver.</hi> 24. That <hi>the Kings of the Earth do bring their Glory and Honour into it.</hi> And at ver. 26. <hi>They ſhall bring the Glory and Honour of the Nations into it:</hi> From whence it is very plain, that the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> was to be a City on Earth. But now, in <hi>Rev.</hi> xxii. 3. The Throne of God and the Lamb is ſaid to be in the <hi>New Jeruſalem;</hi> which Throne of God and the Lamb, is the ſame with that we are ſpeaking of, as will appear from <hi>Rev.</hi> v. 6. where the Lamb is repreſented in the midſt of it. And therefore the Throne we ſpeak of is an Earthly Throne, as being in an Earthly City.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Laſtly, For fail, Dr. <hi>M.</hi> himſelf, againſt whom I unwillingly diſpute all this while, confeſſes the 24 Elders to be a Type of our Noble Reformers, <hi>i.e.</hi> of Mortals: See his <hi>Apoc. Apocalypſeos</hi> upon <hi>Rev.</hi> xi. 16. whence it follows, That the Throne about which they are repreſented in the Viſion, muſt be a Type of an Earthly Throne. Nay, and even this the Doctor has aſſerted too (tho he now ſeem to have forgotten it) or elſe what mean thoſe words of his upon <hi>Rev.</hi> vii. 9. <hi>After this I beheld, and lo, a great multitude which no Man could number, of all Nations, and Kindreds, and People, and Tongues, ſtood before the Throne, and before the Lamb.</hi> Namely (ſays the Doctor) before the Throne above (<hi>viz.</hi> in <hi>Chap.</hi> iv. &amp; v.) deſcribed in Heaven: <hi>For</hi> John (he adds) <hi>is ſuppoſed to ſee all theſe Viſions in Heaven, tho they concern things here on Earth.</hi> Of which words, the plain meaning is, That altho the Viſion repreſents theſe things in Heaven, yet they are to be fulfill'd in things on Earth. And what is this but to grant, that the Throne ſeen in Heaven in the Type, is in the Antitype an Earthly Throne? And ſo much for proof, that by the Throne, <hi>Rev.</hi> iv. &amp; v. is meant an Earthly Throne.</p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore conclude this Point with a further Illuſtration of it, taken from that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is eaſie to be obſerv'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Sitter on the Throne we ſpeak of, and the Dragon with Seven Heads and Ten Horns, deſcribed <hi>Rev.</hi> xii. Concerning which Dragon, it is confeſt by Mr. <hi>Mede,</hi> Dr. <hi>More,</hi> and all the beſt Interpreters, that thereby are meant the Pagan Perſecuting Emperours of <hi>Rome,</hi> the profeſt Enemies and Oppoſers of the Church of Chriſt. Notwithſtanding which conſent of Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, the Holy Spirit himſelf tells us, at <hi>ver.</hi> 9. that this Dragon is the Devil and Satan. And yet the Prophecy mentions but one ſuch Seven-headed Dragon neither. So that it muſt neceſſarily
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:29464:15"/>follow, according to them, (and indeed according to the truth it ſelf) that by the Dragon is repreſented both the Pagan Emperours as Inſtruments, and Satan as the prime mover of them, by whoſe Inſtigation and Aſſiſtance, they became ſo active in endeavouring the Churches Ruine: The Emperours were the viſible Dragon, actuated and ſet on work by Satan the inviſible.</p>
            <p>The Reddition or Application of this to the Sitter on the Throne, is obvious. For by Interpreting the Sitter on the Throne to be a King, (notwithſtanding that the Prophecy ſets him forth as God) I do no more make two Sitters on the Throne, then they who expound the Dragon to be a King (notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he is ſaid to be the Devil) make two Dragons. And as the things ſpoken of the Dragon there, are applicable to Satan as the prime Mover, but to the Emperours as his Inſtruments; ſo the things ſpoken of the Sitter on the Throne, are applicable to God as the firſt and principal Cauſe of all, and to Men employed by him in the Service, only as Inſtruments and ſecond Cauſes. And I would fain know whether the nature of the oppoſite Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that there is between two Princes, the one a violent Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor and profeſt Enemy of the Church, and the other as zealous a Defender of it, do not oblige, that as the one is repreſented like the Devil and Satan, whoſe work he does; ſo the other ſhould be repreſented like God, whoſe Image, Inſtrument and Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative on Earth he is. According as we find Interpreters to agree in the Expoſition of the Man-child, ſaid to be caught up to God, and to his Throne, <hi>Rev.</hi> xii. 5. for they expound it generally of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great (as I took notice before.) And if other Scriptures are found to flie ſo high in the ſetting forth of Kings, as to call them Gods; much more may we expect them to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd as ſuch in this Book of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> which muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt for loftineſs of Expreſſion, to exceed all others in the Sacred Volume.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:29464:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
